Guide to the Mab Segrest papers, 1967-2006
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Mab Segrest papers 1967-2006
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Mab Segrest
21.5 linear feet Extent: 16125 Items
Mab Segrest is a feminist writer, scholar, and activist who received her PhD from Duke University in 1979. During her time in North Carolina, she was on the editorial board of Feminary, the feminist literary collective founded in the Triangle in 1969. She also worked with a group called North Carolinians against Racist and Religious Violence (NCRRV). This inspired her 1994 autobiographical work, Memoir of a Race Traitor, in which she describes working against the Ku Klux Klan in North Carolina. Segrest also worked as the Coordinator of the Urban-Rural Mission from 1992-2000, after which she returned to academia. She is currently chairs the Gender and Women's Studies Department at Connecticut College.
RL.01164
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The majority of the collection is closed for research. Accession 2006-0027 is open to research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Most of the audiovisual components in this accession are not immediately accessible because they require further processing before use. Unless otherwise noted, Technical Services staff need to reformat for use copies of the films.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Mab Segrest papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1991, 1994-1996, and 2006.
Collection Overview
This collection (Accession 1991-058) (6000 items; 8.0 lin. ft.; dated 1967-1991) contains materials documenting Segrest's personal life and education through 1975, and her professional life from 1977-1991)
Addition (1994-086) (2250 items, 3.0 lin. ft.; dated 1992-93) documents Memoir of a Race Traitor and the Third Wave Foundation.
Addition (1995-088) (5625 items, 7.5 lin. ft.; dated 1970-1994) comprises documentation relating to Segrest's professional life, including Memoir of a Race Traitor, the Third Wave Foundation, activism files, and a typescript of Dorothy Allison's Bastard out of Carolina.
Addition (1996-124) (2250 items, 3.0 lin. ft., dated 1995-1996) contains files relating to projects, the NC Coalition for Gay and Lesbian Equality and the North Carolinians Against Racial and Religious Violence (NCARRV), and the Center for Democratic Renewal (CDR)
Preliminary Contents of Collection
- Accession (1991-0058)
  Accession (6000 items; 8.0 lin. ft.; dated 1967-1991) contains materials documenting Segrest's personal life and education through 1975, and her professional life from 1977-1991) Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
  Closed: Accession 1991-0058 is closed to research.
- Accession (1994-0086)
  Accession (2250 items, 3.0 lin. ft.; dated 1992-93) documents Memoir of a Race Traitor and the Third Wave Foundation. Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
  Accession 1994-0086 is closed to research.
- Accession (1995-0088)
  Accession (6000 items; 8.0 lin. ft.; dated 1967-1991) (5625 items, 7.5 lin. ft.; dated 1970-1994) comprises documentation relating to Segrest's professional life, including Memoir of a Race Traitor, the Third Wave Foundation, activism files, and a typescript of Dorothy Allison's Bastard out of Carolina. Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
  Accession 1996-0088 is closed to research.
- Accession (1996-0124)
  Accession (1996-124) (3.0 lin. ft.) contains files relating to projects, the NC Coalition for Gay and Lesbian Equality and the North Carolinians Against Racial and Religious Violence (NCARRV), and the Center for Democratic Renewal (CDR). Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
  Accession 1991-0124 is closed to research.
- Accession (2006-0027), (17 boxes)
  research, speaking engagements, speeches, subject files, teaching materials, Born to Belonging book drafts, Beijing conference
  - Correspondences with Nancy Bereano/Squirrel (Box 1)
  - Souls of White Folks (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Dangerous Liasons (Box 1)
  - What's Sex Got To Do With It, Y'all? (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Rutgers University Press (Box 1)
  - Born to Belonging (Box 1)
  - Beijing Essay (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Pictures (Box 1)
  - Race and Spirit/Mark (Box 1)
  - Women's Studies, 2002-2003 (Box 1)
  - Going to the Chapel (Box 1)
  - Time is Money (Box 1)
  - Am 2 Decision (Box 1)
  - National Coalition for Gay and Lesbian Equality (Box 1)
  - How Democracy Works pamphlet (Box 1)
  - Am 2 Decision (Box 2)
  - Clinton (Box 2)
  - Welfare (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Sher's NCAE piece on NC (Box 2)
  - Hollow Corporation (Box 2)
  - Poverty in NC (Box 2)
  - Poverty, health care, and Medicare (Box 2)
  - Durham County Work First, 1998 (Box 2)
  - Family Matters (Box 2)
  - Forum for the Future (Box 2)
  - Equality for Chinese Women (Box 2)
  - Beijing Forum, 1995 (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Elvis Presley (Box 2)
  - Princess Diana (Box 2)
  - Our Own Place (Box 2)
  - Durham Women (Box 2)
  - Health Day (Box 2)
  - Sexuality Globally (Box 2)
  - CCR (Box 2)
  - GLBT (Box 3)
  - Confessions of a Closet Baptist (Box 3)
  - Michelle's Book (Box 3)
  - Michelle's Letter (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - 1996 day planner (Box 3)
  - Duke courses (Box 3)
  - Farm Labor Organizing Committee (Box 3)
  - UNC (Box 3)
  - Hawaiian Sovereignty/Gay Marriage (Box 3)
  - Born to Belonging (Box 3)
  - Publicity Photos (Box 3)
  - How Am I To Be Heard? (Box 3)
  - Olympics Out of Cobb (Box 3)
  - 4WCW (Box 3)
  - African Health (Box 3)
  - Research notebooks and note cards (3 folders) (Box 3)
  - Durban (Box 3)
  - UN documents (Box 4)
  - Tuskeegee News (Box 4)
  - WEDO (Box 4)
  - Biography of a Chairman Mao Badge (Box 4)
  - Articles and drafts (Box 4)
  - Hawaii (Box 4)
  - Intelligence Report (Box 4)
  - Atlanta/Coke (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - Beijing Plenary (Box 4)
  - Assembly Handbook (Box 4)
  - South Africa/GLBT (Box 4)
  - Africa/Belonging (Box 5)
  - China/Belonging (Box 5)
  - China document/Belonging (Box 5)
  - Epilogue/Belonging (Box 5)
  - Atlanta Chapter 2 (Box 5)
  - Africa (Box 5)
  - Body is Your Subconscious Mind (Box 5)
  - Origins of Post-Modernity (Box 5)
  - Olympics (Box 5)
  - The Public Eye (Box 5)
  - The Question of Equality (Box 5)
  - Book royalties (Box 5)
  - VA Tech (Box 5)
  - Arts Council Program (Box 5)
  - NC Arts Council proposal draft (Box 5)
  - Teaching materials (Box 6)
  - Focus Program at Duke University (Box 6)
  - Research notebooks (Box 6)
  - Southern Queer Course at UNC (5 folders) (Box 6)
  - Linguafranca (Box 6)
  - University of Delaware (Box 6)
  - Papers and drafts (Box 6)
  - Delaware workshop (Box 7)
  - RNEW (Box 7)
  - Time's Witness (Box 7)
  - Iowa City (Box 7)
  - Southern History conference (Box 7)
  - Lillian Smith (Box 7)
  - University of Vermont (Box 7)
  - University of Florida (Box 7)
  - University of Virginia (Box 7)
  - Rutgers University (Box 7)
  - Connecticut College (Box 7)
  - Bifocal Publication (Box 7)
  - Common Ground Beijing (Box 7)
  - Blue Mountain (Box 7)
  - Reed College (Box 7)
  - Notes and drafts (Box 7)
  - University of Delaware (Box 8)
  - UNC (Box 8)
  - Day planners, 1997-1999 (Box 8)
  - Women, Risk and Faith (Box 8)
  - Connecticut College (Box 8)
  - Spiritual Warfare (Box 8)
  - Down South, Up South, and Out South (Box 8)
  - Duke papers (Box 8)
  - Leadership at the Crossroads (Box 8)
  - University of Alabama (Box 8)
  - Tyrell (Box 8)
  - National YWCA (Box 8)
  - UNC Women's Studies (Box 8)
  - SLGC speech (Box 8)
  - Greater Cleveland Roundtable (Box 8)
  - Homophobia and Women's Studies (Box 8)
  - Windcall (Box 8)
  - What's Sex Got To Do With It, Y'all? (Box 8)
  - NEH Fellowships (Box 8)
  - Reader's Companion to US Women's History (Box 8)
  - Memphis (Box 8)
  - Tacoma (Box 8)
  - Paper abstracts (Box 8)
  - The Making and Unmaking of Whiteness (Box 8)
  - No Easy Walk (Box 8)
  - FSC speech (Box 8)
  - Unitarian (Box 8)
  - Dialogue on the Lesbian and Gay Left (Box 9)
  - The Conservatism of the Heart (Box 9)
  - San Diego (Box 9)
  - Regional Economic Justice Network (Box 9)
  - Mother's Voice press conference (Box 9)
  - Republican Platform, 1996 (Box 9)
  - Research notebook (Box 9)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 9)
  - Born to Belonging drafts and book cover (4 folders) (Box 9)
  - Email printouts (Box 9)
  - Born to Belonging draft (Box 10)
  - Born to Belonging draft (6 folders) (Box 11)
  - What's Sex Got To Do With it, Y'all draft (Box 11)
  - Hawaiian Sovereignty draft (Box 11)
  - Hawaii (Box 11)
  - Welfare Reform Bill in NC (Box 12)
  - Albany, NY's LGBT community, 1999 (Box 12)
  - No Easy Walk (Box 12)
  - Honolulu (Box 12)
  - Les*Beijing (Box 12)
  - Elvis (Box 12)
  - What's Sex (Box 12)
  - Durham Women (Box 12)
  - UCC (Box 12)
  - UUA (Box 12)
  - Social Justice Employment Program (Box 12)
  - Building Bridges (Box 12)
  - Bridges (Box 12)
  - Braden (Box 12)
  - John Younger (Box 12)
  - Planning (Box 12)
  - Job (Box 12)
  - Duke Women's Studies (Box 12)
  - Roberson Scholars (Box 12)
  - Job application (Box 12)
  - Southerners for Economic Justice (Box 12)
  - Anti-racist pedagogy (Box 12)
  - NGLTF Report, 1967 (Box 12)
  - Newsletters (2 folders) (Box 13)
  - Beijing, 1995 (Box 13)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 13)
  - Resumes (Box 13)
  - University Scholars Program (Box 13)
  - Job ads (3 folders) (Box 13)
  - Tyrell recommendation (Box 13)
  - Reconstruction or Deconstruction? (7 folders) (Box 13)
  - Reviews (Box 14)
  - Teaching materials (5 folders) (Box 14)
  - European Parliament documents (Box 14)
  - Searchlight (Box 14)
  - New Era (Box 14)
  - The Point (Box 14)
  - Raleigh News and Observer clippings (Box 15)
  - Extra magazine (Box 15)
  - Southeast Regional Justice Network (Box 15)
  - Highlander (Box 15)
  - Southern Echo, inc. (Box 15)
  - Workshop handout (Box 15)
  - Strategies for Working (Box 15)
  - Amnesty International gay materials (Box 15)
  - Media mergers clipping (Box 15)
  - To Have and Have Not (Box 15)
  - Militia (Box 15)
  - In These Times (Box 15)
  - NCCGLE, 1994 (Box 15)
  - HIV (Box 15)
  - Economic articles (Box 15)
  - Jubilee (Box 15)
  - Mab's 50th birthday party (Box 15)
  - Birthday and condolence cards (Box 15)
  - Birthday and assorted correspondence (Box 15)
  - Beijing letter of acceptance (Box 16)
  - Laura Flanders article (Box 16)
  - Jim Sears correspondence (2 folders) (Box 16)
  - Center for Democratic Renewal (Box 16)
  - Professional correspondence, 1996-1997 (5 folders) (Box 16)
  - Day planner, undated (Box 16)
  - Rose Norman article (Box 16)
  - Interview with Segrest (Box 16)
  - Western Kentucky University (Box 16)
  - Feminary article (Box 16)
  - Review (Box 16)
  - Independent article on Segrest (Box 16)
  - Waiting for Hillary (Box 16)
  - Keynote address, 1995 (Box 16)
  - Whose American History (Box 16)
  - Book publicity (Box 16)
  - Speak Out, 1994-1995 (Box 16)
  - Review (Box 16)
  - Going to the Chapel (Box 16)
  - Contemplating Matt Shepherd (Box 16)
  - Louisville speech (Box 16)
  - Creating Change speech, 1993 (Box 16)
  - Souls of White Folks (Box 16)
  - Out in the South chapter (Box 16)
  - Memoir of a Race Traitor (Box 16)
  - Responses to memoir (2 folders) (Box 16)
  - Book materials (Box 17)
  - Affirmative Action (Box 17)
  - Anthologies (Box 17)
  - Articles @2 folders) (Box 17)
  - Gay Pride program, Mexico, 1996 (Box 17)
  - CDCA (Box 17)
  - Beijing (2 folders) (Box 17)
  - Thomas Merton Center (Box 17)
  - Alternative radio (Box 17)
  - Louisville (Box 17)
  - Giard (Box 17)
  - Jim Sears (2 folders) (Box 17)
  - Astrea (Box 17)
  - UNC Press (Box 17)
  - Testing the Limits (Box 17)
  - Virginia Woolf (Box 17)
  - Research (2 folders) (Box 17)
  - Articles on feminism (Box 17)
  - Sisters and Queers (Box 17)
  - Professional correspondence (3 folders) (Box 17)
  - Workshop materials, 1995 (Box 17)
  - Keynote address, 1995 (Box 17)
  - Expert witness, 1994 (Box 17)
  - Fellowship application (Box 17)
  - Speeches (3 folders) (Box 17)
  - Center for Public Television (Box 17)
  - Abstinence until marriage (Box 17)
  - Kentucky Foundation proposal (Box 17)
  - Book marketing materials (Box 17)